Straight from the Hart, because HVAC
cleaning should be a positive experience.
And, you know, that has a
couple plays to it.
It should be a positive
experience, meaning
that's the method that
we're going to discuss
is positive air duct cleaning, as
opposed to negative air duct cleaning.
And, you know, it should be positive.
It should be a fun thing.
It should be a
joy for everybody doing it.
Welcome to Straight
from the Hart, because
HVAC cleaning should
be a positive experience.
I'm your host, David
Baker, and today I'm joined
by RamAir International
founder of CEO David Hart.
In this launch episode, David shares the
story behind positive air duct cleaning.
And the RamAir equipment that's
transforming businesses.
And the real customer wins we'll
be featuring in the weeks ahead,
including our first guest, Bob
Jordan of PuroClean Northwest.
If you're in the HVAC
restoration and duct
cleaning industry and
want practical insights
to actually move the needle you're in
the right place, let's get straight to it.
Here's David Hart.
David, how are you doing today?
Great, thanks, Dave. How's it going?
Doing well, doing well.
What's going on there in Oregon?
A lot of duct cleaning.
Good.
As I think you probably know, in addition
to RamAir, I also have an HVAC cleaning and
de-contamination company
out here, and we are
absolutely slammed with everything from
residential to commercial to restorative.
That's terrific.
Hey, we're launching a new show.
It's Straight from the Hart.
Talk about that.
Why are we doing this and
what's our content going to be?
Well, I think this is the
right time to do this, Dave.
Duct cleaning has been around for a
long time since the 1950s, and the way it's
been done has been with
a traditional method that
was fine for the day based on the construction
of ducting that was being cleaned.
The construction of it has evolved,
and yet the methodology hadn't.
The equipment, the methodology, all was the
same, and it was kind of stuck in that deal
until about 18 years ago when
another method came up, came about.
And the reason I say, I think this is the
right time now, rather than 18 or 10 years
ago, or whatever the
case may be, is there's
been so many discoveries
about methodology
and which is superior and which
can do things that the other can't.
And I'm not going to
get into all that right
now, which is kind of, you know,
we're opening the door to this.
That's going to be the fun stuff we're going
to be able to talk about, exactly, this
episode and all these
future episodes to come.
I'm just excited to be able to do this
with you. Straight from the Hart, okay?
My last name is Hart, so there you go.
And I am going to give it to you straight.
And the other part
of that title is
Straight from the Hart because HVAC
cleaning should be a positive experience.
And you know, that has
a couple of plays to it.
It should be a positive
experience, meaning
that's the method that
we're going to discuss
is positive air duct cleaning as
opposed to negative air duct cleaning.
And you know, it should be positive.
It should be a fun thing.
It should be a joy for everybody doing it.
Our customers, when
we do duct cleaning for
people, man, we have
so many five-star reviews.
People type in, "My son's
asthma is all but gone."
"We're breathing better."
"I'm not dusting
every single day."
So it is.
It's just a positive thing.
I like how you say our customers because
RamAir sells equipment to professional
remediators who then
perform service for customers
and you think in the
mind of your customers
for the end customer,
how you make their life
better. How do you make their life
a more positive experience, right?
Well, it's funny you would
say that because, yes, I do.
And the reason I do is because I
am one of our customers also, okay?
It's like the Hair Club for Men
[HairClub].
I don't just own the company.
I'm also a client, right?
We don't just design and manufacture
groundbreaking air duct cleaning equipment.
We use it every single day out in the field
and we are so busy, especially right now.
I'm operating in the field.
In fact, yesterday I spoke
with you on the phone.
I had to get going
because I was in the middle
of a Forensic Restoration
job where we were
doing a mold remediation job and so, yeah,
we are using the stuff every single day.
Yeah, that's great.
So let's talk about some
of the benefits to end users.
So let's talk about the four.
We talked about four key benefits of
the positive air duct cleaning method.
And the first one is a one-person job.
You can do one person,
can do the whole job.
Talk about that.
Yeah.
Well, in our company,
we send each van and
team out. And I put team like
that because it is one person.
It's one-person routes and
they do two houses per day.
Get back usually between
four or five in the afternoon.
So there you go.
That's amazing.
I mean, you save so much
on labor and you can
actually make quite a bit of
profit then on a job, per job.
Sure.
Now, you can send two out.
Any more than that, it's
getting be quite a few.
I mean, you can have a helper go, you know,
it's a hand stuff and maybe be doing some
and it does go very, very
smoothly with two people.
I'm not knocking that.
It's just that it works
so well with one is
designed around one if
you want to have a second.
You know, it's nice.
So one person-jobs. The second
thing is that it's noninvasive, right?
Talk about that.
It's a noninvasive approach
to air duct cleaning.
Right.
And what does that mean?
Noninvasive.
Well, in this particular
case, they way we
are using that term,
we are not cutting a big
hole into the HVAC system in
order to hook equipment up to it.
And in the traditional way that the
ducts are cleaned, that's what takes place.
You pull up with either
a truck mounted or a
portable machine that
sucks at large quantities of air.
You cut into the duct
system and you extract
the air from the ducts,
creating negative pressure inside.
It's why it's called
negative air duct cleaning,
creating negative
pressure inside those ducts.
And we're going to get a lot into that
later in this and future episodes as well.
But ,ours is
noninvasive because
we're not bringing that
mass air mover to the job site.
That mass air mover is already there.
You know, for successful HVAC
cleaning, you need three elements.
You need mass air movement,
agitation, and vacuum.
Now, the mass air movement, which is, as I
mentioned, the machine that they bring up
and cut into the ducts, I said that
ours is already there and delivered.
It's the air handler, the furnace
fan, the air handler fan itself.
And it's not only delivered to the job
site, it's already hooked up to the ducts.
It's ready to go.
And even better yet, we leave it at the job
site when we're done we just leave it hooked up.
So we don't have to take it back, clean it
out, maintain and all that kind of stuff.
It did the job for us.
Secondly, in regard to that, it's the right
amount of air flow for the job we're doing.
Now, if we're doing a
residential home, say a
2500 square foot house,
we have an air mover
that is moving that air
at the correct amount
of speed for that
particular duct system.
Not too much, not
too little, it's just right.
Now, if we get into a
commercial job, and my
personal HVAC cleaning
company has done eight
casinos in the last few
years, these are huge,
huge hundreds of thousands
of square feet of space.
They don't just have little
residential air handlers in them.
They have air handlers on the rooftop
that are the size of shipping containers.
You walk into these things.
They're not, they're not
moving 2000, 5000, even
15000 CFM of air
movement, which is considered
a lot for negative air
machine to move 15000 CFM.
That's a lot.
These things are pushing
60000. 60000 CFM of air.
So what can you bring that they
don't already have, right?
Right.
I mean, what are you going to drive a
duct truck into the middle of a casino?
You can't do it.
So you're going to have to use
the portables, and that's
just, oh my God, it's
going to take forever.
We did a casino a
couple of years ago down
in California, where
they had gotten a quote
from another company that was going
to charge, I'll just go ahead and tell you.
This is called Straight
from the Hart, right?
I love it.
I'm going to shoot it straight.
We're going to, right,
they were going to
charge $750,000 to spend three
months to go in and clean these ducts.
That's invasive into a casino when you have
people who, by the way, are also drinking,
and walking around
in this place for you to
be running your show
there for three months,
sectioning off areas
and all that kind of stuff.
They want it done quickly.
They want it done well, but
they also wanted done efficiently.
We did that job in 10 days. Granted we did
it for half as much, but I'd rather make
$300k and some in 10
days than $750k in three months.
Yeah.
Opportunity costs. Because then
you go on and do something else.
Absolutely.
No.
It's actually higher.
It's considerably higher
revenue generation.
So it's a very, it's a great system.
One person job, it's a minimally invasive.
Also, you don't need not
to have the commercial
stuff, but for the residential, you
don't need an HVAC license, right?
I mean, you have a patent on this
SaniJet decontamination application system.
The decontamination
system, the SaniJet, is
probably my favorite
aspect to the whole thing.
And the reason being
is there are other ways
of cleaning ducts than
the positive air method.
Are they good for the ducts?
Do they do as good of a job?
Once again, we're going to
get into that in future episodes.
But in order to apply
a decontaminant to the
inside of a duct
system, in the event of a
restoration job, whether
it be a smoke, crime
scene, unattended
death, homicide, suicide,
illicit drug, mold,
whatever we're going
to be applying to
those surfaces, the inside
of the duct walls,
there's two golden rules
in the restoration
industry that everybody in
the restoration industry
is familiar with, and that is:
You need to coat
the surface completely
and has a dwell for a
certain amount of time.
And the traditional
way of applying a
decontaminant to the
inside of an HVAC system, and
I use the term
decontaminate, rather than
disinfectant, because
you use a disinfectant
if it's a pathogen,
whatever the case may
be, illicit drug, you're not killing
anything because there's nothing living.
So it's a chemical neutralizer
in that particular case.
So I use the word decontaminate to cover
both disinfectant and chemical neutralizer.
So you can hear me using
that term a lot, decontaminate.
Now if you're going
to apply that to the
inside of a duct system,
the way it's been done
traditionally for
decades is fogging, you
always hear about them,
and a fog the ducts, okay.
And the way that's
done is to put the
decontaminate liquid
into a fogging machine, and
then you turn on the
air handler of the duct
system, go to the
return duct, and blast that
fog into the return
duct with the air handler
fan moving, which carries
it through the duct system.
And at first that
sounds great, it sounds
like it works, it carries it
through the duct system.
But let's examine that
preposition for a moment, through.
It applies it through the duct
system, not to, not on, okay.
So how does that look?
And I know this, because I've been,
I've been doing this for over 30 years.
I've had my HVAC cleaning
company for 28 years.
Positive air duct cleaning
has existed for 18.
So what did I do for
the previous 10, right?
Okay, I was there.
I was doing it, all right.
So you go to the return,
you fog the decontaminate
into there, it carries
it through the duct,
and you watch those supply ducts where the
air comes out, those registers, and you can
see the fog start
to pour out of those,
meaning it's now going
through the duct system.
What happens is the person
applying it then shuts the fog off, okay.
We're now fogging the inside of
the space, I've done the fogging.
The thing is, if you shut
off the fogger at that point,
you haven't even begun to
coat the inside of those ducts.
The only way you will
have coated the inside
of those ducts, if you
keep fogging to the
point, that all that
fog comes out of those
registers, you want to
be able to see through
the room, you want to
see your hand in front
of the face, you would
have filled the interior
of the space, you got
decontaminate all over
every surface, it's
on the duct surfaces,
but it's also on the
walls, the ceiling, the
floor, the windows,
all the contents within
that structure, and nobody does that,
nobody would do that in their right mind.
So they shut it off early,
and nothing ever gets done.
Now, the SaniJet, which is the patented
system that we designed about 15 years ago,
we turn the HVAC
system off, so the air is
not going through the
system, we have through
a compressed canister,
we filled our liquid as
a long hose, at the end
of which is a dispersion
ball, we depress the lever, it fogs it
out of that ball, and sprays it directly to
the duct walls as we
slowly retract that hose.
So now it gives us
complete control over
applying that
decontaminant to those duct
walls, and none of it
enters the living space.
So yeah, it puts exactly
what you want, where
you want it, and it doesn't
put it where you don't want it.
You're not going to
get the fog all over the
house, and you're getting
more disinfectant inside the room.
You're going to get exactly as
much as you want where you want it.
That's great. That's terrific.
Well, great.
Thank you.
This is going to be a lot of fun, and
we're going to be talking to customers.
You've got a bunch of people lined up, and
we'll be hearing from their perspective on
what it's like to have RamAir equipment,
and how they can be successful operating
a business, to have a positive experience,
and give people a positive experience.
We got some really
great guests lined up on
absolutely stoked, especially
our first one, Bob Jordan.
He's a former aerospace
engineer that got into restoration.
He now owns a PuroClean franchise.
He's written a book on ditigation,
and he's going to be our first guest.
We have a gentleman
who is paramount in the
manufacturing of flex ducting, so he
knows the manufacturing of it very well.
We have some other restorers, as well
as users of different equipment out there.
It's going to be a real, real
fun trip we're going to take.
Well, that's going to be great.
I look forward to it.
We'll talk next week.
[MUSIC PLAYING]