WELCOME TO STRAIGHT FROM THE HEART BECAUSE
HVAC CLEANING SHOULD BE A POSITIVE EXPERIENCE.
I'M HERE WITH DAVID HART, FOUNDER OF RAM
AIR.
DAVID, HOW ARE DOING TODAY?
GREAT, THANKS, MORNING DAVE, HOW YOU DOING?
WHAT'S GOING ON IN OREGON?
WHAT'S HAPPENING THIS WEEK?
KEEPIN' BUSY?
IT'S MEMORIAL DAY WEEKEND.
AND THIS IS A RESORT TOWN HERE IN BEND WHERE
I LIVE.
SO IT IS PACKED OUT THERE.
BUT YEAH.
WELL, LISTEN, TODAY WE'RE GONNA TALK ABOUT
UH HVAC CLEANING SHOULD BE PART OF ANY RESTORATION PROJECT, RIGHT?
UH IT SEEMS LIKE AXIOMATIC, LIKE OF COURSE,
BUT TALK TO ME WHY PEOPLE DON'T THINK THAT WAY AND WHY WOULD THEY SHOULD THINK THAT WAY?
YOU KNOW, THIS IS SOMETHING UM THAT BECOMES
MORE AND MORE OF SOMETHING ABOUT WHICH WE TALK AS AN INDUSTRY.
YOU KNOW, I'VE BEEN DOING THIS FOR LIKE 30
YEARS IN THE CLEANING AND RESTORATION INDUSTRY.
STARTED RAM AIR 18 YEARS AGO.
THAT'S WHEN POSITIVE AIR DECK CLEANING WAS
BORN, ACTUALLY 18 YEARS AGO.
AND MORE AND MORE, ALL THE TIME, I'M FINDING
THIS TOPIC COMING UP FINALLY.
THE RESTORATION INDUSTRY IS WAKING UP TO THE
FACT THAT, YEAH, WE NEED TO INCLUDE THE LUNGS OF THE BUILDING INTO THE RESTORATION PROCESS.
YOU KNOW, I GO TO AROUND.
LIKE THEY WOULD CLEAN THE WHOLE PLACE, BUT
THEN LEAVE HVAC ALONE.
I MEAN, IS THAT EVEN POSSIBLE?
WHY WOULD THEY DO THAT?
WELL, UH THE EXPERIENCE CONVENTION IN LAS
VEGAS, WHICH IS THE BIGGEST CLEANING AND RESTORATION CONVENTION IN THE UNITED STATES, POSSIBLY EVEN THE WORLD EVERY YEAR, IT'S IN
LAS VEGAS COMING UP THIS SEPTEMBER.
IN FACT, UH I DID A PRESENTATION A COUPLE
YEARS AGO ON THIS TOPIC AND IT WAS ALL RESTORERS AND CLEANERS OUT IN THE AUDIENCE.
AND I JUST, I DON'T EVEN KNOW IF THEY KNEW
THAT MY TOPIC WAS HVAC AT THIS POINT, BECAUSE WHAT THE NAME OF THE PRESENTATION WAS PANEL OF EXPERTS.
THERE WERE FIVE OF US.
THERE WAS UH TWO PHDS, JEFF JONES, UH BARRY
COSTA, AND MYSELF.
AND AS SOON AS I GOT UP ON THE STAGE, I
ASKED THE AUDIENCE, SAID, WHAT IN YOUR EXPERIENCE IS THE MOST IGNORED OR IMPROPERLY DONE PORTION OF EVERY RESTORATION JOB YOU'VE EVER KNOWN?
AND LOT OF HANDS WENT UP AND I STARTED
POINTING TO PEOPLE, HVAC, HVAC, HVAC.
IT WAS THE ONLY ANSWER, AND IT'S THE CORRECT
ANSWER.
IT'S BEEN THE MOST IGNORED PORTION.
MOST RESTORATION JOBS THAT I'VE BEEN ON
PRIOR TO MY GETTING INVOLVED IN IT, THE HVAC WASN'T EVEN DONE.
AND THAT DOESN'T MAKE ANY SENSE.
IT'S PART OF THE STRUCTURE.
NOW, AT MICROBIAL WARRIOR, WE ALWAYS MENTION
STRUCTURE AND CONTENTS, RIGHT?
AND INDOOR AIR QUALITY, THOSE THREE THINGS,
RIGHT?
NOW, THE INDOOR AIR QUALITY, OF COURSE, IS
LARGELY AFFECTED BY THE STRUCTURE AND CONTENTS.
BUT WHAT IS THE HVAC?
THE HVAC IS PART OF THE STRUCTURE AND IT'S
ALSO A CONTENT.
AND IT'S THE PORTION OF THE STRUCTURE
RESPONSIBLE FOR MOVING THE AIR THROUGHOUT THE ENTIRE STRUCTURE.
NOW WHEN YOU'RE MOVING THE AIR, WHAT ELSE
ARE YOU MOVING?
WHATEVER'S IN THE AIR.
YOU'RE MOVING CONTAMINANTS.
SO TO NOT INCLUDE IT ON EVERY SINGLE
RESTORATION JOB, WHETHER IT BE SMOKE, CRIME SCENE, UNINTENDED DEATH, HOMICIDE, SUICIDE, ILLICIT DRUG, MOLD.
UH YOU'RE JUST NOT DOING THE JOB COMPLETELY.
WHY WASN'T IT DONE BEFORE?
IS IT BECAUSE THEY JUST DIDN'T HAVE THE
EQUIPMENT?
THAT'S NOT WHAT THEY DO?
OR THEY COULDN'T BILL FOR IT?
IT'S EXTRA WORK, IT WOULDN'T BE UH CHARGED
THROUGH INSURANCE?
WHAT WAS THE PRIMARY REASON?
YEAH.
I'M GOING TO START WITH THE MOST RECENT ONE
YOU SAID, AND THAT WAS THE BILLING POINTS.
UH XACTIMATE, A LOT OF RESTORATION
COMPANIES, DARE I SAY MOST, GO WITH XACTIMATE.
AND UH UNTIL RECENTLY, THERE WAS ONLY TWO
XACTIMATE LINE ITEMS FOR HVAC CLEANING AND DECONTAMINATION.
NOW, BOB JORDAN, WHO WAS WITH THE UH ONE OF
OUR INTERVIEWS, UH HE AND I WORKED TOGETHER ON DOUBLING THE NUMBER OF
LINE ITEMS IN XACTIMATE FOR HVAC.
SO FROM TWO TO FOUR, OKAY?
BUT THAT'S STILL HECK OF A LOT BETTER.
CAN GET PAID FOR THE WORK YOU DO.
YOU AND ANY, YEAH, YEAH.
GET PAID WELL.
THAT'S A LET'S TOUCH ON THAT BECAUSE THAT'S
VERY IMPORTANT I WANT TO TOUCH ON THAT BUT BUT MORE TO YOUR MOST RECENT QUESTION.
WHY HAS IT BEEN IGNORED?
I THINK A LOT OF IT IS ALSO OUT OF SIGHT OUT
OF MIND YOU KNOW WHEN YOU SEE UH SOMEBODY AND THEY GOT SKIN CANCER YOU KNOW IT YOU CAN SEE IT OR LIP CANCER ANYTHING LIKE THIS LUNG
CANCER THEY CAN'T SEE YOU KNOW AND THAT LIKE
I SAY IT IS THE LUNGS OF THE BUILDING.
IT'S VERY IMPORTANT
ONE MIGHT EVEN SAY THAT THE LUNGS ARE UH ONE
OF THE MOST IMPORTANT PARTS OF THE BODY.
WELL, THE HVAC SYSTEM IS ONE OF THE MOST
IMPORTANT PARTS OF THE STRUCTURE.
I THINK IT'S BEEN A COMBINATION OF, FIRST OF
ALL, THERE HASN'T BEEN THE METHODOLOGY IN ORDER TO DO IT.
UH THE TRADITIONAL WAY OF CLEANING HVAC
SYSTEMS UH HAS BEEN SHOWN TO EXACERBATE THE ISSUE BECAUSE IT'S PULLING UH
MAKEUP AIR FROM THE STRUCTURE INTO THE DUCTS
AS IT'S DOING IT.
YOU JUST, NEVER CATCH UP.
YOU'RE CONSTANTLY RECONTAMINATING WHAT
YOU'RE CLEANING.
SO UNTIL VERY RECENTLY, WITHIN THE LAST
YEAR, THE METHODOLOGY HASN'T BEEN ADOPTED.
NOW, WHEN JEFF JONES OF MICROBIAL WARRIOR
ASKED ME TO WRITE THE STANDARDS AND COME UP WITH THE METHODOLOGY FOR A FORENSIC RESTORATION OF HVAC UH IN WHICH MOLD FALLS BECAUSE, YOU
KNOW, IT'S A BIOCONTAMINANT.
UH
WE CAME INTO THIS VERY ROOM RIGHT HERE, MY
LAB ASSISTANT AND I, AND WE SPENT TWO MONTHS AND WE JUST HAMMERED OUT M THE PROCESS FOR DECONTAMINATION RECHECK AND WE NAILED IT, MADE
IT BULLETPROOF.
AND WHAT ARE RESTORATION PROFESSIONALS
SAYING NOW?
NOW THAT THEY'RE GETTING, THEY HAVE THE
XACTIMATE CODES, NOW THAT IT'S BECOMING MORE EXPECTED TO CLEAN THE LUNGS OF THE BUILDING, UH THEY NOW THEY CAN FOLD IT IN, THEY CAN
HAVE EQUIPMENT THAT'S EASIER TO MANAGE AND
RUN AND USE AND MORE PROFITABLE.
ARE YOU SEEING UH TRACTION IN THE
RESTORATION PROFESSIONALS?
BIG TIME, BIG TIME.
FOR EXAMPLE, WHEN I WAS AT THAT PANEL AT THE
EXPERIENCE A COUPLE YEARS AGO AND I MENTIONED IT AND EVERYBODY SAID HVAC IS THE MOST IGNORED.
AND THEN I CAME BACK WITH, KNOW, IT'S ALSO
VERY IMPORTANT AND NEEDS TO BE DONE.
I COULD SEE THE HEADS NODDING IN THE
AUDIENCE.
EVERYBODY KNOWS.
WE ALL KNOW THAT IT HAS TO BE DONE.
GONNA SPEAK AGAIN AT THE EXPERIENCE, RIGHT?
THIS FALL.
WHAT'S THE TOPIC?
IT'S AN EXCITING ONE.
AH IT'S IN REGARD TO A RESEARCH PAPER THAT
WAS PUBLISHED BY THE CLEANING INDUSTRY RESEARCH INSTITUTE.
THEY HAVE A BIANNUAL JOURNAL THAT COMES OUT
CALLED THE JOURNAL OF CLEANING SCIENCE.
AND IT'S A VERY SERIOUS SCIENTIFIC UH
JOURNAL.
AND THE COVER STORY, THE COVER STORY OF THAT
JOURNAL ACTUALLY IS A RESEARCH PAPER THAT COVERS EXACTLY WHAT WE'RE TALKING ABOUT, METHODOLOGIES OF HVAC CLEANING.
WOW.
THE PRESENTATION IS GOING TO BE ON THAT.
I'M GOING TO BE UH ON STAGE WITH JOHN MILES,
WHO IS THE CHIEF SCIENCE OFFICER FOR SUPERSTRATUM, FANTASTIC COMPANY THAT MAKES MOLD DECONTAMINATION CHEMISTRY.
HE'S ALSO HIS CAREER PRIOR TO THAT POSITION
WAS IN THE FLEX DUCT MANUFACTURING SECTOR.
HE WAS ACTUALLY ON THE TEAM THAT DESIGNED
THE VERY ADHESIVE WITH WHICH FLEX DUCTING IS MADE.
SO YOU COULD SAY THAT.
OUT OF THIS MAN AND A HANDFUL OF OTHERS KNOW
MORE ABOUT FLEX DUCT ADHESIVE THAN ANYBODY LITERALLY IN THE WORLD.
AND I'M GOING TO BE HONORED BY SHARING THE
STAGE WITH HIM AT THIS PRESENTATION.
IT'S GOING TO BE A REALLY COOL PRESENTATION.
COULD JOIN UH OUR SERIES HERE AT ONE POINT?
IT'D BE NICE TO HAVE HIM ON.
AM CONFIDENT THAT I'VE ACTUALLY SPOKEN WITH
HIM.
HE'S EAGER TO DO SO,
TERRIFIC, THAT'S TERRIFIC, THANK YOU.
WELL, THAT'S GREAT.
WE SHOULD BE, UH THAT'S A LITTLE TEASER FOR
WHAT'S COMING, BECAUSE IS IT PUBLISHED NOW OR IT'S SOON TO BE PUBLISHED OFFICIALLY?
CAME OUT THIS, WHAT'S TODAY, FRIDAY?
IT JUST CAME OUT FOUR DAYS AGO, YEAH.
IT IS OUT.
IN FACT, I DIDN'T EVEN KNOW IT HAD COME OUT
YET.
I WAS WATCHING EVERY DAY TO SEE WHEN IT WAS
GONNA COME OUT, BECAUSE I KNEW THAT THAT HAD MADE THE COVER STORY, AND I'M LIKE, OKAY, I GOTTA WATCH THIS.
I GOT A PHONE CALL OUT OF THE BLUE FROM
BARRY COSTA.
HE SAID, CONGRATULATIONS, YOUR RESEARCH
PAPER JUST CAME OUT.
I'M LIKE, HOLY CRAP, THANKS, RIGHT?
YEAH.
THAT'S FANTASTIC.
SO HE'S THE ONE THAT BROKE THE NEWS TO YOU.
YOU GOT IT FROM BARRY.
WELL, THAT'S FANTASTIC.
WELL, WE SHOULD START TALKING ABOUT THIS
NEXT WEEK.
MAYBE WE CAN START TO UNPACK THAT A LITTLE
BIT MORE BECAUSE IT'S BIG NEWS.
IT'S GOING TO BE A SEISMIC SHIFT IN HOW UH
HVAC COMPANIES APPROACH UH HVAC LENDING.
EXAGGERATION.
IT'S ACTUALLY BEING CALLED THE MOST, UH THE
BOMB, THE BIGGEST BOMB EVER DROPPED.
AND NOT A BAD BOMB.
I MEAN, IT'S A GOOD BOMB.
IT'S AN INFORMATIONAL BOMB.
RIGHT.
UH THE BIGGEST INFORMATIONAL BOMB DROPPED ON
THE HVAC CLEANING INDUSTRY IN HISTORY.
UM SO IT'S PRETTY COOL STUFF.
WELL, I CAN'T WAIT TO TALK ABOUT IT WITH
YOU.
HAVE A GREAT MEMORIAL WEEKEND.
ENJOY YOUR BOAT, ENJOY YOUR WEATHER AND LOOK
FORWARD TO TALKING TO YOU NEXT WEEK ABOUT THE BOMB.
AND YOU AS WELL, DAVE.
THANK YOU MUCH.
THANKS, DAVID.