Hey David, you there?
Can you hear me?
Yes, I'm here.
I I'm trying to I've never used river side and it's asking me a lot of different to close
out of I don't like I don't know what it's
Yeah, I got a message that says John's mic is and cam are already in use.
Ask them to close it's all apps, whatever that means.
Yeah.
don't know what the only a the only other is my Windows I can or or not Windows, but
Google.
Let me see if I close that.
If that allows it.
hmm.
Weird.
Yeah.
I can hear you obviously, so your mic is fine.
Can you turn on your uh video?
That's what it's it's it's like you can turn off the camera while recording but you can't
switch cameras.
Um, you wanna just restart your computer and maybe that's the clean way to do it.
I don't know.
Yeah, let's see what I can do here.
Okay, yeah.
Be right back.
Is David is uh you and I gonna be is is is David Hart gonna be on this too?
Okay.
early and he gives me a hard time for being late, so it's my turn to give him a hard time.
There we go.
Alright, let me try this.
Test, test, test.
Mm-hmm.
Test, test, test, test.
Looks pretty good.
Hmm.
Yeah.
Morning guys, sorry I'm a few minutes late.
Well.
I'm just I'm just laughing at the periodic table.
That's all.
Oh shit, do I still have this thing on?
Oh crap.
Okay.
That's that's my normal attire.
I guess I should professionalize a little bit here for for this.
Yes.
John had John was having some trouble.
So he was rebooting his computer and and joining back up in a second here.
So the technical difficulties.
put can you I'll be back in one second.
Sure.
You wait.
Just stay there.
I mean, but just run it.
It's all good.
You're back already.
Tun.
So you went from uh I'm not ready for LinkedIn now to let's go with LinkedIn.
Hold on, let's go to LinkedIn in like three hours.
Is that just because Carrie is so compelling?
Probably.
Well, you know, I got to thinking about it and I knew how much it meant to you.
No, I'm just kidding.
Well, no, because it I mean it might sound like grandiose for me to talk about how
important II CRC is, but really, I mean, if have you seen the way these people treat I I
mean, every single day I see post after post, people are like, Hey, look at my I CRC
certificate.
They're huge, they're all over the world, they're the biggest
certification body for cleaning and restoration in the world.
And if they adopt positive air dog cleaning and let's say bring us on as an instructor,
dude, it's I the minute that happens, I'm going on helicopter trader.
I'm looking for my from an for buying a helicopter.
You know, and it's not just about money.
I'm I'm talking about how we will have impacted the industry to the point where now and I
think this paper and and backing like like did you see what Kerry Lesage wrote?
Yeah.
I mean detailed.
Oh yeah, she did
highly respected.
She's super highly respected.
She knows a lot of people.
And and so I think rather than me posting it on there, hey, look what I did.
You know what I'm saying?
It just it means more.
Yeah.
And so and it just kind of clicked in me.
I thought, well, you know what?
Well, let me see if I can make this happen.
And she actually offered to uh well, she said, she said, you ought to post it on LinkedIn
and I'll share it.
I said, I tell you what, you post it on LinkedIn and I'll share it.
I had no idea she was gonna say all the awesome things she did.
but she went in detail.
It was great.
Yeah, it was terrific.
Yeah.
D now do you know her personally out outside of this?
We've met briefly.
She wouldn't remember me, but I I remember.
Yeah.
Actually I we met uh first time when you did the panel of experts.
That's when I met her in person the first time too.
Actually, it's the only time we've met in person.
And I was really impressed with her articulation and just how personable and fun she is.
She's just a really super cool lady.
I mean, she's the kind of person I could like not just do business stuff with, but go hang
out for the evening and have a good old time.
Yeah.
I mean, we were sitting at a table and I I was there were stiffs like like Jeff Jones and
Barry Costa at the table.
You know what I'm saying?
I'm kidding.
I know.
Yeah.
Ki kinda.
Hey.
How's it going, John?
got to work here.
Terrific.
look at him.
Look at him.
Now Dave Dave's gonna tell you how to sit and how to all that.
I'm gonna say if you could back up a little bit.
Try we'll try to get all of our heads in and David Hart, you could lean in a little bit.
Well I can I can always I can I can expand it.
That's okay.
Yeah, but try to perfect.
That's perfect.
You see your just sort of shiny forehead.
John John missed my what I was gonna wear.
Uh I came on with this and and David Baker's like, No, that's not professional.
I'm whatever, dude.
I didn't realize this was such a stiff show, you know.
a stiff show.
Although that you that would work.
It would certainly would get eyeballs.
There's no doubt about that.
John, nice to meet you.
It's nice to meet you.
Yeah, thanks for thanks for taking time to to to chat about the the paper.
It's really exciting.
Really exciting stuff.
Yeah.
let's let's let's talk show order a little bit.
Here's what I was thinking, guys.
let's let's just kind of walk it through a little bit, just get the scaffolding, and then
we can go in.
We'll try to keep it conversational, but I wanted some structure to it.
Um, so my thought was I'll do a quick intro.
I'll introduce David and then um
Which yeah, David, you're not gonna introduce yourself.
Okay, never mind, sorry.
Yeah.
Please.
Uh silence all phones, please.
And uh David, what I would love for you to do is just give a quick, you know, uh I'm gonna
say, hey, you know, this is great.
Exciting this paper's come out.
Yeah, you know, y say something about the reaction you're getting and how excited uh it's
really you know, whatever you wanna say about it.
And then in a nutshell, give me like one sentence on what it is.
Don't go into it yet.
Just give me like what's what's what's the paper and what do we what you know, kind of
like m something we've been working negative uh negative air, which has been industry
standard.
I whatever you want to say.
Whatever you want.
I just what I'm saying is I just want you introduce the paper quickly, but
it by the by its title, which is structural incompatibility of negative air cleaning in
flexible HVAC duct systems.
and in the abstract, that first sentence in the abstract is pretty good.
So you can say that, but I I don't think I'll need you to read it as much as you can if
you want to.
But I want to get through it quickly because you have a way with like long in elongating
your sentences or or paragraphs.
Okay.
But but then I'll have you introduce John.
I think that that that format works pretty well.
I introduce you, you you're you're with me, and then you d introduce John.
You you talk about how you work together, whatever.
the why it's important to have him on and why it's important to get his his take on the
results of this report.
And then we go into it.
And then uh John, you could you can say hello.
And then we're not going to do backgrounds quite yet.
I wanna you can look you can lead into it into the with in the story, but I kind of want
to jump right in uh and get at it.
so the first question would be like, well what is what is negative air duct cleaning?
What are flexible duct systems and why are they incompatible?
That's our first one.
Think that's it.
So my thought was that's the first one.
You just just structurally, why they're different.
You know, you talk about, you know, I get the notes in there.
Like, why do flex duct, why does that not work with the negative error alone?
Second, then once we get into that, I'll we'll get into like, okay, well, what are the
consequences?
What are the failure modes?
You could talk, and I think I think there's three failure modes, right?
Isn't that what you guys discussed?
Or is there one that has two implications?
I couldn't really tell.
what what l what are the three as you understand them, David?
I have them in the notes here.
I got uh
adhesive scene peeling and delamination, linear collapse, and perforations in holes.
Are those is it is it correct to think of three or is it two or does it one with Okay.
Okay.
Around the wire coal.
Dave, Dave, what do you what are your thoughts on?
I mean sorry I'm sorry, John, what are your thoughts on?
Yeah, mean, that's the pressure of the polyester pushing on the wire will expand in and
the wire is not going to move.
It's structurally forced, but once it relaxes, it's going to have natural pull.
One side is going to go back to its original state and the other one is going to try to
stay there.
Then adhesive has got to withstand those forces.
That's why you need to be the guy answering that question.
I I I I couldn't have borden like that, yeah.
or holes.
And we could talk about it proportionately if it's if it's predominantly, you know,
adhesive scene peeling and delamination.
If that's primarily the thing, you know, we can lean into that.
We can also talk parenthetically about the other two, linear collapse or
you know, John, in my opinion, the holes and whatnot, I to me that's kind of a s the only
reason that would really happen is because I mean, when you have two layers of something
that are stuck together, for lack of a better term, it's going to be stronger than if
there's a small separation between the two.
Just why that's exactly why I can rip a phone book in half.
And good God, I wish we had one right here.
I'd show it because if you s if you separate the pages and create a little space in
between each page, you can rip it in half.
Try to f
Dude, Arnold Schwarzenegger can't rip a phone book in half that's all tight.
And you know what I mean, John, right?
So by the the space, maybe that's what creates those holes.
Would you concur with that?
In fact, I just now thought of this.
Does that make sense?
also the mechanical brushing of that environment under that negative, that still that
negative pressure.
um Yeah, whatever.
I don't know all the different types of.
on a second on the whipping.
So hold on a second because according to a sh here's what I you tell me if this is not
good, but what I was thinking is it's the the structurally it's flex ducks were not
designed for negative air pressure.
That's point one.
Point two is the consequences of that.
You get the delamination, you get the uh wire, and then you got the whole the holes,
whatever.
The third thing, and do we want to talk about the the mechanical side?
Because the report says that that's the predominant.
Problem.
That's where the most damage comes from, the mechanical agitation.
the pressure itself does the delamination.
The agitation, okay, mechanical agitation exacerbates that.
And what not, John?
that's exactly what's happened.
from the order, we're gonna talk about the pressure first.
Okay.
And then we'll get in then we're gonna that's gonna roll into then mechanical.
Is
this is really good.
This should be recorded.
Yeah, this is we're doing it.
Okay.
any cuts, we can.
We'll we'll we can edit it together.
And if you if it's if you at point some point stumble, just pause and start your sentence
over thinking, well, that's a good place where I would do a cut.
So I can just lean lean right into it.
Uh so it's designed Flex Duck is not designed for negative air.
There are consequences because the negative air pressure.
That's number two.
Number three, we get into that okay, there's also mechanical agitation.
So it's not just the air, but it's also mechanical agitation.
David, uh positive air positive air product cleaning doesn't have the same mechanical is
it is that a difference?
does have the same mechanical agitation, which can be in the form of either air blast by
way of a skipper ball, whip, or brush.
And we do implement all three of those in different circumstances.
And by the way, I just want to point out real quick, flex duct was never meant to be put
under negative pressure beyond what it would normally experience in a return duct.
Okay.
It can handle a certain amount, just not a whole hell of a lot.
Well, here's my point about the mechanical.
Do we really want to spend yes, it's true, but whether you do it positively or whether you
do it negatively, you're still gonna get the mechanical.
Do we talk about it all?
Or is your point, well, you're gonna have the mechanical, but it's because of all the
negative air pressure, then the mechanical exacerbates it.
Mechanical alone isn't so bad.
if you think about it, because what you want to do is you wanna keep sorry.
Yeah.
alone is not a problem.
Mechanical alone does not destroy the duct.
Mechanical alone is not an issue.
It's because the negative air pressure on top of the mechanical.
Is that true?
correct.
I would say that's true and I would add to that that negative pressure alone can and does.
It's just that the it's just that the agitation exacerbates it.
You know, because if it
but my the reason I'm bringing this up, this is important.
The reason I'm bringing it up is you also have mechanical.
So someone might conclude, oh well positive error is mechanical too, so either way.
So I just wanna make sure we don't we might make that clear.
If we're gonna go into mechanical, why is it why 'cause
I want you guys to...
never nobody's ever gonna nobody's ever gonna clean a duct by simply subjecting subjecting
it to pressures either positive or negative.
There's always gonna be mechanical adaptation implemented.
You were gonna say something, John?
So someone else might say don't clean them though.
So but that's what's happening.
the fact that, you know, if you're thinking of my hands being the layers on the duct that
are in this tube, okay, and the wires wrap around.
In that particular phase, when you put the vacuum on it and it unseparates itself, now
you've got this flapping piece of polyester that's standing there, and then when that
mechanical whip comes around, what's it do?
It grabs it.
There you go.
That's what I want.
Because then the positive doesn't get there, so the mechanical is not a problem.
But because you've had the delamination and the pull apart, then the mechanical is a
problem.
Be okay.
Okay, then we can do it.
You you guys both rock.
We're just trying to keep up with you, ma'am.
then so just to just be clear, we're gonna talk about structurally, it's not there for
negative air.
Uh here are the things that can go wrong with negative air pressure.
And then after with since these things can go wrong, then you do mechanical can really be
a problem because you've already, you know, whatever that is, you you it becomes a real
big issue.
The fourth thing is then, and the big issue of all this is that you don't see it.
As a as a homeowner, you uh or even as a contractor, you can't tell.
You have you have no idea damage is going on underneath, right?
So that's an easy next
you get the mold frickin' problem that's the result.
Do you think I should have should I bring some of this on the camera at some point?
I don't have any
some yeah, huh?
Yeah.
I think
damaged unfortunately.
I send all that to the lab, but
want to illustrate a point, pull it out and show it.
Rather than just holding up and like a like, hey, look, it's in my hand.
This is a duct.
Sh if you're trying to show like the circumference or bend it or something, then do that.
Okay.
hold it up then I'll put the hat back on.
Sure, you can, whatever.
It'll be fun.
Okay.
So we've talked.
I'm gonna, I'm sorry for being repetitive, but it's gonna be design, then the problems
with pressure, mechanical issues, and the the fourth thing is but but you can't see it.
That's the that's a real that's the heartparting part.
And if you don't see it, you don't address it, it can cause the fifth one is issues,
right?
You can have condensation, you can have mold, people get sick.
It's a real problem, right?
you've now opened that environment that allows unconditioned air, high humidity, to be
able to seep in to that cold environment.
Because now that you have that little flap open, you've got cold air cooling on those
wires, cooling on all those things.
And if it can seep in there, will form on all those cold, you you can't bring a cold drink
outside in the South without condensation form on it in seconds.
And so the same thing will happen there.
and then you have mold in the house, you you mitigate the house and you still have
problems 'cause it's in the air ducts, right?
You got mold in the air ducts.
Okay.
new mold spores are being leached through the whole system.
Okay, so it's structurally designed.
he keeps mentioning that flap.
You know, we have that in the article, there's that image from the lab that shows that.
That'll be a good time maybe to show that image of that flap.
'Cause it shows that from the lab.
Yeah.
problems, then it's negative air, the consequences of what negative air does.
It's exacerbated by mechanical.
Um, the big problem is you can't see it.
That's a real problem.
And then the fifth is that, well, it caught it causes condensation, mold issues.
There's all sorts of problems that can do be c come from this.
just mold, but i contaminants alone, period, come in.
Yeah.
number five.
Number six is there are there are way there are ways you can mitigate against this.
There are ways that if you're an egg of air duct cleaner, you can I didn't look at these,
but you seem to suggest you told you said there's a number of things that you can do to
but but of course you can do those things, but the problem is who's gonna do them?
It becomes costly, maybe they're not quite as effective.
It's still you still have you can miss.
I don't know what the what your key points are, but that's okay, good, say it.
And I'm gonna use that word.
And then of course, seven is finally then well, what's the solution?
Here's all the problems.
You know, you can't really it's really not really doable.
Positive airduct cleaning.
That's the solution.
That's that's a whole different way, that's a whole different approach, that's a whole
different method.
And you can talk about that.
And then finally
a gun to your head and pull the trigger, but you know what?
You can also just go hundred and eighty degrees that way and no problem.
I mean, you know, they're Yeah.
Exactly.
I don't think we use that analogy.
and then finally, if you want to talk about industry stand industry standards, like right
now, there's no real uh delineation on duck cleaning.
There's no real way.
I don't know if you want to get into that, but I think it's a good one to talk about.
Like where does a where does the industry going?
Where should they go?
Where should standards go?
Of course, it's gonna support.
mention microbial warrior as like trailblazers in that they have implemented that into
their standards.
And um, you know.
Okay.
I'll try to keep the, you know, we'll be editing this, but you know, so we go off, we can
get back on.
That's okay.
So I'll start off with the show, uh introduction, and then I'll introduce you, David.
You'll say hello.
You're gonna get the buzz about the paper.
What's it quick quick thing about what it's about, introduce John, and then we're on.
Sound good?
All right.
Sounds great.
Not just good.
Absolutely great.
Give me one second here.
Have you ever seen the movie Jobs with Ashton Couture?
Let me get one thing straight.
We don't do fine.
We do great.
Welcome to Straight from the Heart, because HVAC cleaning should be a positive experience.
I'm David Baker.
Most HVAC contractors see traditional air dire sorry.
Welcome to Straight from the Heart.
Because HVAC cleaning should be a positive experience.
I don't want to say it that way.
I'm going to do it again.
Welcome to Straight from the Heart, because HVAC cleaning should be a positive experience.
I'm David Baker.
Because sorry, we haven't had this much trouble before.
You're being a little fast too.
Okay, slow down.
Okay, good.
I'm a little nervous.
Welcome to Straight from the Heart.
man.
Sorry.
with that.
Welcome to Straight from the Heart, because HVAC cleaning should be a positive experience.
I'm David Baker.
Most HVAC contractors see traditional negative air cleaning as the standard for duct
cleaning.
But a new report shows negative air cleaning is structurally incompatible with flexible
duct systems.
Today we unpack what that means, what the lab found, and the implications it has for
contractors who perform HVAC cleaning.
David Hardis, founder and CEO of Ram Air International and author of this new report.
David, how are you doing today?
Great, thank you, David.
What's going on with this report?
Are you getting some reaction to this breaking news?
Yeah.
It just came out, I'm gonna say roughly ten days ago and it's really making waves already.
Uh 'cause it's it's it's pretty profound.
Yeah.
Tell us before we get into it, we got a lot to cover, but and we have our guests we'll
introduce, but before we do that, what's what's the gist of this report?
Okay, well I'll read you the title.
it is structural incompatibility of negative air cleaning in flexible HVAC duct systems.
And that's what the paper is about.
It's about the negative air duct cleaning method, which was devised back in the 50s and
has remained the traditional way of cleaning ducts, how it's incompatible with the ducting
that's dominated structures since the 1980s, flex ducting.
It was designed originally for metal ducting.
And then the implementation of flex ducting into the building of structures, the the
methodology used in the cleaning did not evolve with it.
that's a that's a big news because that's the most widely used uh method used, right?
So before we get before we get into it, let's let's introduce our guest.
Who do we have here today?
John Miles.
I've known John for years.
Incredible guy.
One of my favorite people in the industry.
He's just a brainiac.
he is formerly uh the way he's so impacting in this paper is because of a sentence that he
said to me a couple of years ago in a meeting I was having with Superstratum, which is the
company that makes the mold chemist mold decontamination chemistry that we use in our
cleaning company.
And
It's just knocked it out of the park for us every time.
I love Superstratum.
And we had a meeting with him and the CEO, Seth Jones.
And out of the blue, because this is what scientists do, have a we have a blurting issue.
We just happen to just say things as they pop into our heads.
Out of the blue, he happens to say, David, you know, I really like the way that you clean
HVAC systems because you use positive pressure.
Flex ducting was never meant to be under negative pressure.
And
All of a sudden it was like a record scratch.
Okay.
It's like, excuse me?
Uh, could you say that again?
And Seth Jones, the CEO of Superstratum, laughed.
He goes, Yeah, I thought that might get your attention, David.
I was like, Yeah, you got my attention, brother.
Let's hear what you have to say.
And then John went into this brilliant um description of how flex ducting is made, because
John actually was uh designed.
Uh you're gonna word this better than I did, uh, John, but the adhesive, the seam seal
adhesive with which flex ducting is made.
So you could literally say,
That this guy knows more about seam seal adhesive with which flex acting is made than
anybody in the world.
And so, you know, what he had to say was was pretty important.
And that's what started this whole research.
Uh anyway, I'm gonna turn it over to John.
John, uh tell us about yourself.
Name's John Miles.
I'm a chemist by education.
Went to the Citadel.
Been in the adhesive, water-based adhesive development all my career, 35 years.
So started off as technical service and developing different types of coatings, all
basically water-based, and then into sales and sales management.
But in that career, I worked with the polymer producer.
I worked for polymer producers that manufactured the base polymer
sold to the adhesive manufacturers that sold that finished product onto the flexible duct
markets.
One of the characteristics, the main characteristics of a flexible duct and that adhesive,
because it's a two and a half inch, two inch strip of polyester, so it has to have good
adhesion to that polyester, but what it needed was high shear strength.
It has very, very low peel strength.
The shear strength is when you're putting pressure
against something you have that ability you know if you're looking at it in this direction
it won't move but the little flap on it has no peel strength to it very little and so when
you put negative pressure on something on this side it flaps up very very easily
So that's it that's what we're gonna go into first because the the report really talks
about that the the structure of flexible duck duct systems really isn't designed for
negative air pressure.
It's because of the flaps, predominantly because of the flaps are are one direction.
I I described it as like petting a cat from the tail to the head, something like that.
Is that similar to the concept or
be, yes, that'd be a good concept.
For for us for us, you know, neophytes.
Is that the primary issue then, the flaps?
Is that the st main structural problem with uh the the way that flex ducting does isn't
compatible with negative air duct cleaning?
Well, it's because of the difference in the strengths.
The sheer strength on it can withstand 20 times the amount of pressure put against that.
And this is all in the specs from the flexible duct manufacturers and has what, 10 % of
the same amount under the vacuum.
So that alone should tell you the, you know, what...
which you should always should be doing positive pressure if you're going to be cleaning
these particular ducts.
Keep them what they were manufactured to do and not move it into a different direction
where the adhesives or the structure alone, the wire structure can withstand that negative
pressure.
I'd like to quickly clarify, if I may, the difference between shear strength and peel
strength.
And this is this is how I understand it, John.
Of course, you're the expert, so you know, uh jump in anytime.
But when you have two uh surfaces that are adhesed together, uh the shear strength is is
the s the slide um coefficient, shall I say.
Uh, the peel strength is if you were to pull them straight across.
For example, I think that's one of the things that makes a post-it work so well is the low
peel strength and the high shear strength.
And it the way you explained it to me, the way I understood it was you can't have both.
If you're gonna have a lot of shear strength, you're gonna sacrifice peel strength and
vice versa.
And when you div when you designed the adhesive with which flex ducting is made, you went
all out on shear strength.
Because it's a called a forced air duct system for a reason.
It's meant to have, if you look at a tube, okay,
Of ducting, it's meant to have air force into it, so you're gonna get pressure this way as
it expands due to that positive pressure.
You put negative, you put it under negative pressure, pull the air out from the inside,
you're gonna get it pulling this way.
And because flex ducting is two layers of of poly uh sheeting that are glued together with
a metal coil down the middle for support, when you put pressure from the inside, negative
pressure, you're pulling that inner layer.
of of plastic apart from the outer layer and it doesn't take much.
Like you said, 20 times the the positive pressure it can handle.
Negative pressure tolerance is between one half inch to one inch negative stratic
pressure.
That's water column.
Okay.
One half to one inch, the the positive pressure is ten inch.
So it can handle literally 10 to 20 times the amount of positive pressure.
So would would you concur with that, uh John?
And the reason is that everyone knows that through these ducts, they absorb a huge amount
of oil deposits from fragments of the skin, all the things that's going in there.
And that oil, when it comes in contact with the polymer, if it is a very tactful polymer
that has high peel strength, it will soften it too much.
So the shear strength properties
is with a polymer that has great shear strength, okay, and has resistance to that oil.
So it's two-fold why the adhesive was developed the way it was.
It was so that it would not, over time, the oil deposits and the dirt and debris in there
would not lose the performance of that adhesive, but then also maintain that high shear
strength.
If you went to a more softer polymer, straight acrylic or something like that, yes, it
would have incredible peel strength and have good resistance
But then it would have no resistance.
The oil itself would absorb into that and it would get very mushy and it would lose all
that performance.
People see that when you have different, or not a post-it note, but real high-tech things.
What do you do to get that label off the good, you put a little bit of oil and it gets
really mushy and it comes off.
That's exactly what would have happened in the flexible duct had you used an acrylic-based
polymer for that.
Sounds you put a little bit of thought into this.
So clearly the you know, th these are not designed for negative air pressure.
They're designed for positive air pressure, positive airflow, maybe some negative air
pressure, but not a lot.
What are the
pressure that would be generated by the return portion of the HVAC system, which you like
again is not very much.
So
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And what we say it did we talk about what negative air pressure is?
I didn't know if he defined it.
Does everybody know what like it's it's what is negative air pressure?
What is negative air duct cleaning?
John, you're the you're the you're the scient you're the scientist.
sucking in, know, kind of just like your regular vacuum that you have at your house.
um And you're literally putting it in an environment and sucking that debris.
But the walls of that will pull in at the force of what's coming from the vacuum.
So that's the whole concept of that.
Yeah.
And then negate and then neg that's good.
Negative pressure sucks.
And it sucks backwards, right?
It's the different flow.
Positive is through the through positively from where from the from the system.
Yeah.
And then yeah.
So so it's not designed for neg strong and negative air pressure.
What what are the consequences?
Talk about that.
Like cause your report identifies some of the damage and some of the
ways that negative heavy n negative air pressure can impact the structure and uh what are
the consequences?
Once again, John, I I can't compete with your articulation, so please, if you would.
naturally, that cross slap we were talking about, once it pulls from that, now you've got,
it's not gonna re-adh- there's no re-adhesion of these types of polymers.
So once that flap opens, then you're gonna have unconditioned air to be able to migrate in
there.
Also, the wire that's on there, if it deforms, there's nothing to push it back out.
So the, and so now you've got a deformed, oh flexible duct.
So that's,
you know, those are two major areas that you're gonna get.
And naturally once that deforms or that flap is opened up, when you do the mechanical
sweeping or something in there, it's gonna grab a hold of that little piece and rip it
even further.
And then...
So the more it rips, the more the it's like a snowball effect.
It sounds like.
Yeah.
once it comes undone, like I say, it's not going to open up.
Now for...
you know, if you ran a camera back down there and you said had positive back on it, it may
lay up against it.
Okay, when you're looking at it and don't see anything, but once it relaxes, that flaps
going to come down, that unconditioned air is going to come back in and then you're going
to turn the unit on and it may go back up, but you just keep sit.
mean, it's fooling you thinking it's repaired and it's not.
And once unconditioned gets in there, we all know that a cold glass in the South is going
to make condensation.
That is a
environment, spores and mold and all the different debris that's in an attic or in a crawl
space where these ducts are, all that air is going to now be entrapped, going to grow
mold, going to grow contaminants.
And what are you doing?
Just forcing that through your whole house.
You you just did create one problem.
You just pushed it in all the different rooms.
One thing I'd like to ask you, John, um, because when you transitioned, and by the way,
I'm from Oregon, so we got to be careful with that word transitioned, but when you
transitioned from uh flex duct manufacturing to the design of mold decontamination
chemistry, uh, did you say that you've noticed how much mold is growing in HVAC systems
after having been subjected to negative air duct cleaning?
Did I hear that correctly?
mean, people that get their duck cleaned and then...
we see it a good bit that they have more issues and then we come to find out their damage
from the negative error.
So that's honestly in my business in offering a chemistry that neutralizes the organics
and oh detoxes these systems from the microtoxins that could be produced from the molds.
uh What we recognize is that by partnering with somebody like David in the recommendation,
is using POSIT that they don't initially, those homeowners that are having issues with
their home, they don't create another problem behind it.
So you use the right proper technique of cleaning the ducts, then you decontaminate the
duct with our chemistry, the building cleaner, and then put a protectant with the
Endurance Coating Pro in that.
And then those particular customers don't have those issues, at least in the lungs of the
home.
This is what you're breathing and what you're circulating throughout the home.
The lungs of the home, that's a really good analogy.
I use that one myself.
Yeah.
What but the structure is still compromised.
Even even now it's clean and it's good, it needs to be clean, but you're still compromised
from the negative air deck pressure that you had.
If you cleaned it with negative air.
Now I think that John was suggesting that you do clean it, but you use positive pressure
in the process.
Yeah.
Right.
So talk about uh w you may have this on your home.
You may get cleaning, but you don't like I my ducks are fine, I've had it cleaned, they
look great.
But the problem is you can't really see or detect whether or not your your ducks are
compromised.
Somebody who has lung cancer looks great.
You know, you can't see it, doesn't mean the problem's not there.
there's typically a layer of uh insulation around flex ducting.
Uh you can't see the damage that's been done.
John, concur?
right.
The only way you'd be able to see it is with some type of video through the actual duck.
But the internal portion of that duck has been compromised now.
And now you've put it in an environment that it wasn't meant to be in if unconditioned air
is getting into that environment.
And so that's the big problem.
even a camera down there, I don't believe would also would uh always show the damage.
In fact, if you look at the images that were supplied by the laboratory that provided the
results for this research paper that did we did, which by the way, uh this laboratory, we
went all out, okay.
Shot for the stars on this one, you know, and that's the way I've always liked to do
things, it's just shoot for the almost ridiculous.
Okay.
Then if you come up short, you're still pretty, pretty awesome, right?
So I reached out to what I can found to be the ultimate laboratory to do this testing.
In fact, they actually do testing for uh Military Department of Defense and NASA, things
like this.
And they actually took on the project for us, which I thought was really, really cool.
And they have some images in the report that they supplied for us that it show a uh
enlarged view of the delamination, which you might not see with a naked eye or a camera or
something of that nature.
You had talked about um okay, so you do negative air duct cleaning, it can be real
problematic.
Um, well, there's different ways you can mitigate against it.
If I'm if I use negative air duct cleaning, well, you not really, but technically there
are things you can do to help address it.
Talk about that and why those are are not really uh doable.
There are things that you can do.
I mean, nobody in the right mind ever would.
And here's what they are.
Okay.
Because first of all, if you're going to clean an HVAC system and you want to use negative
error, you need to decipher whether or not there is any flex duct within that network of
ducting of that structure.
Okay.
And that's going to be more than just asking somebody or even looking at the blueprints,
because there may have been some remodeling done to some of that.
Maybe a piece was re uh what was was replaced at some point.
Uh
Otherwise completely metal, but now there's a flex duct section in there.
So it's going to take eyes on throughout that whole system.
So first step, decipher whether or not there's any flex duct in it.
That means getting eyes on every foot of ducting within that structure.
Who's going to do that?
That's ridiculous.
Okay.
It would take forever and all that.
But let's say you do.
Okay, well, now you need to decipher whether or not that flex ducting has a one-half inch
or a one-inch.
Negative pressure tolerance, because those are the two different tolerances that that are
out there by manufacturers.
Uh, that's going to require you to find out the make and model of that ducting, find out
which pressure tolerance it is.
Who's going to do that?
How could you do that?
So, because you can't or won't, you need to just assume that it's the weaker of the two,
one half-inch flex negative pressure.
So
After crawling through the entire structure to decipher whether or not there's any flex
ducting, then deciphering whether it's one half inch or one inch negative static pressure,
and then assuming that it's half inch, now you need to set up pressure monitoring devices
throughout that flex duct in order to ensure that you don't surpass those tolerances,
which you're going to.
Okay, I've I've talked with so many negative, negative former negative uh pressure uh
people.
That have just been straight up honest with me.
And one one individual even was one of the uh top NADCA National Air Duck Cleaning
Association's instructors.
He was with them for 30 years.
he was actually an international liaison for for that organization.
And he said, Look, he said, when we hook up negative air pressure equipment to a duct
system, we we we hook it up until we get that flex duct just shaking, and then we back it
off a hair.
Now, if it's shaking.
What kind of what kind of pressures have we got there?
All right.
He said that we create such negative pressures, we have actually flattened metal ducting
before.
Now, if you're flattening metal ducting, tell me that, tell me you're not surpassing one
inch negative static pressure.
So back to back to the process though.
Deciphering if there's any flex duct, deciphering what the tolerance is, setting up
monitoring equipment and monitoring it constantly during that negative pressure.
Nobody's in their right mind, even you know, nobody even
out of their right mind would do that.
It's it's it's insane.
It's asinine.
Okay.
And the whole thing was even brought up just to show the asinineness of it.
So you could do all that or just do what you should do.
And that is use positive pressure and and get the job done, get the job done right.
Did you in the in the paper did you test positive and near air duct cleaning, or is it all
just focused on the implications and the effects of negative air duct cleaning?
The the paper focuses on on the negative uh pressures.
We didn't go heavy into the positive because the positive pressure tolerance is so high.
It's like like like like John said, it's it's ten to twenty times the amount that you're
never gonna you're never you're gonna come close to that.
we know that because it's using the HVAC system to do the positive air duct cleaning.
So the the the actual pr air pressure that the system was designed for is what's being
used to clean the ducts.
Is that fair to say?
Yeah.
utilizing the uh air handler, uh, air movement in the process, which by the way has has
other awesome attributes.
For example, when I teach our courses here, uh we teach, you know, training and
certification courses in positive air declining here in Bend, Oregon.
Uh, we have a lot of people that transition from negative air declining to positive.
And a lot of them will say, you know, I get tired of getting things stuck on the dampers.
Okay, now this is whole nother topic, and I don't want to go heavy into it right now, but
but you know, any when you have a multi-zone system, you typically have trunk line and
then you have branches that come off of that.
And at that branch to trunk intersection, there'll be a damper.
It's a flap that opens and closes to allow or disallow airflow into certain sections of
the structure.
Now, when they build a structure like a home, there's almost always construction garbage
that gets done in there, chunks of wood, chunks of sheetrock, lunch wrappers.
Um, I mean, tools.
I've pulled every I pulled seven bricks out of a duct one time.
People stuck them down in there in order to divert airflow.
I pulled 24 pieces of silverware out of another another duct system one time, and it was
the good, expensive silverware.
It was in a hundred year old home.
We figured that back in the depression, we know that a lot of people uh would hide their
valuables in ducts.
How do we know that?
Because for 28 years, I've pulled valuables out of ducts of homes that are pre 1930.
Okay.
So all these things are always in the branch.
They're not in the trunk line.
They're in the branch.
And when you're doing negative error, you're pulling in reverse of the direction that was
intended by the engineering of the HVAC system.
And all that big stuff, those chunks of wood, chunks of sheetrock, and everything I just
named, have to go past that damper, they get stuck on that damper, or worse yet, damage
that damper.
And now you've just made the whole situation worse.
So, you know, there's there's more than more than just this pressure reason to get away
from from negative error methodology.
In I I want to talk about one more thing about positive air duct cleaning and then move on
to the industry standards.
Positive air duct cleaning, you have your Santa jet and it it's a ball and it sprays out
um formula to disinfect or disinfectants inside.
That's the super stratum, right?
That's what we're talking about, right?
Along with the Santa jet.
It's whatever decontaminant you want to apply for whatever reason.
there's there's times and places in in order to apply a decontaminant.
And once again, I use that word rather than disinfectant because let's say we're doing
meth or fentanyl decontamination, you're not disinfecting it.
There's no pathogens to kill.
You're chemically neutralizing it.
So in order to combine disinfectant with chemical neutralizer, I simply use the word
decontaminant.
But in order to get that into a duct system, the traditional way.
was to fog it.
We've all heard of fogging a duct system.
I'm gonna fog the ducts.
And the way that's done is to take a fogging machine, put your chemical in there, and then
blast it into the return duct with the air handler running and it carries it through the
duct system.
And at surface value, that sounds like it makes sense.
It does carry it through the duct system.
But then again, let's examine that preposition through as opposed to onto okay.
It carries it through the duct system.
And I've done this, okay, because I've been in this industry for over 30 years.
And SantaJet's only been around for 15.
So I did the same thing everybody else is doing, which is to fog it.
And you blow it in through the return and you watch the supplies until that fog starts to
come out of the supply ducts and you can see it entering the room and you shut your fogger
off.
That's what everybody does.
But golden rule from apply for applying a disinfectant is there's two golden rules: coat
the surface completely and allow dwell time, right?
Well, if you're not going to coat the surface completely, you're not going to achieve what
that decontaminant is supposed to do.
The only way you will really have coded all that ducting is if you continue to fog and
you're watching all that fog come out of the return or the supply ducts, and you fill that
structure so full of fog that you will have coated the tabletops, the windows, the wall,
the ceiling, the you will have coded the interior structure and contents to the point of
just absurdity.
And nobody does that.
Nobody would.
And so therefore, fogging a duct system doesn't work.
It can't work.
So we came up with Santa jet, which is a compressed air canister that has a long hose, and
on the end of that hose is the ball to which you referred that has 13 holes, has six holes
45 degree angle backward, six holes 45 degree angle forward.
And by the way, they're they're staggered for a starburst effect.
And we have one at the very tip that shoots it straight forward.
We run that down into the duct, depress the lever.
It it mists the the decontaminant along the side of the duct and you slowly retract that
through the duct with the HVAC handler turned off so that there's no airflow, nothing
blows into the structure.
You're putting a hundred percent that you could decontaminate exactly where you want it to
be, zero percent where you don't, and it gives you a hundred percent control over how much
you put in there.
And yes, super stratum is what we use for mold.
And I tell you what, ever since we switched, you know, because I've been doing this
forever.
Superstrat, how long you been?
was the longest yes I've ever seen in my life.
You warned him.
You warned us.
Yeah.
man, I get on the phone with people.
I'm like
let me tell ya.
Well, you use super stratum for the decontaminants.
Remember, we got to focus on that.
As a disinfectant, it's not the chemistry is focused around the organics that are left in
that environment.
Now there are some properties that that chemistry has that could be that, but the EP
regulates that language on that.
So we're focused around the organics and the removal of those things.
And you're using the right amount.
Because also when you're following something at the beginning, you're saturating a whole
lot of there before even a little bit just comes out the end.
And so you're wasting a lot of chemicals and you're putting much more stress on all those
adhesives again because you've got this water saturant that is just dripping in there.
And it's just not, it's not a good practice to have that much water, you know, in your
HVAC system.
It will take a little time for it to dry out when you follow like that.
And the so the point is that positive air duct cleaning works quite well hand in glove
with uh super stratum uh solutions, and it should be the way it should air duct uh HVAC
cleaning should be a positive experience.
But let's talk about the industry now.
Like what what's going on with the industry?
What standard where does it I don't think the industry really differentiates between
negative air duct cleaning and positive air duct cleaning?
They don't really have a voice on that.
What what's happening there and where should things go?
What should happen next until
For the industry to how should the industry react?
You know, a lot of industries are slow to evolve.
you can have new methodology that is superior, and it will take forever for the industry
to really adopt it.
I will say that positive air dye cleaning, the it is very, very widely used.
In fact, uh I've personally trained people in several countries.
We have come, we just had a group from Bermuda actually come and get trained and certified
by us.
so there are users of positive air diet cleaning in every major city, the United States
and twenty-four foreign countries.
Bermuda was our twenty fourth.
Um so yeah, it's it's very widely used, but but still uh
The traditional method still dominates the industry.
But the industry does the industry say anything about negative versus positive air?
No, the industry hasn't addressed it.
And I think that's a couple of reasons.
I think that the positive air duct cleaning methodology is new enough that it hasn't
gotten into the conversation enough yet.
And, you know, getting people to change something, people don't like change.
Especially old organizations that have been around forever and they make money by the
methodology they've been preaching for years, to to sit there and say,
You know what?
That doesn't work anymore.
You get they're not gonna be real big on jumping.
don't we in the interview we'll cut that part 'cause we don't need to to throw any shade
at the industries, right?
I don't think you want to.
Yeah.
I'm just I'm just knowing what you said about IR C R C so.
throwing shade, but honestly, think part of it is because I think they're a little
embarrassed, honestly, uh because David pointed this out um and none of them recognized
that the adhesive and the structural design has all been written for the last 40 some
years with flexible duct that one is much stronger than the other, but no one took notice
of that.
And for that, I think is the biggest problem.
where I think they're basically, don't know how to move forward because if they
acknowledge they made a mistake, then they've got 40 years of having to deal with people
coming back with that, oh, that's the reason why I'm sick in my home and these other
things.
I don't know what the industry, I think we're doing the right thing by bringing it up and
we'll see how they react, but it's gonna be curious.
We're following the science, right, David?
I know you like that, David.
We're following the science.
What does the data say?
It kind of reminds me of and I shouldn't say reminds me because I wasn't around back then,
but when doctors used to medical doctors used to uh promote cigarette smoking as a healthy
thing to do.
And then it's like, guess what?
You know, it's not.
Um, you know, it like like John said, it's embarrassing to to to the industry that has
supported that for so long.
Anyway, well thank you both for for talking through this report and it's really exciting.
This is uh as we said, a seismic shift in the industry and we're looking forward to
hearing more.
any final thoughts?
No final thoughts.
No, please cut that.
Please don't put that in there.
I'm gonna put that at the front, at the beginning.
You have the intro?
No thoughts.
No final cut the final.
like with Bill Clinton, I don't have the answers.
Yeah.
the answers, right.
Okay, well let's do a little goodbye then.
Okay, well thank both.
Thank you, John, for for joining this conversation.
Thank you, David, for this great report.
We're looking forward to see uh great things from this new study.
Sounds great, thank you.
And by the way, um if you want to do that again and do your seismic shift, I think that
was beautiful.
By the way, seismic shift is fucking cool.
shift.
I know I keep using that one.
That's a good one.
What did I say?
I can't remember.
I I uh I think I think I said it okay the first time.
I'll we'll use that one.
Yeah, but then I f'd it up.
But anywho.
Well, let me do one more take just in case.
well thank you both for for joining uh joining this uh discussion of this report.
It's gonna be a seismic shift in the industry.
It's really, really exciting.
John, thank you for for joining this call.
And David, congratulations on this new report.
We're looking forward to seeing great things.
Thank you, David.
Thank you, John.
That's it.
All right.
Thank you.
Anything are we we okay?
D did that go okay?
I thought we had covered a lot of good stuff.
I think so.
And and we have a couple for the blooper reel too, so that's good.
Yeah, we got a we got a lot of bloopers.
We have a a whole you know section of bloopers over the last number of s episodes we've
done.
We should, yeah.
I've been I've I've been holding I haven't really thought through how we're gonna do it
yet.
But yeah, we should.
Yeah.
on a serious note, seriously, John, that was freaking I d I mean, by far, and no, I don't
tell everybody this, our best guest, man.
I mean, hands down.
think Second was Clay, but you're best.
you're number one so far.
thank you.
One out of two.
don't no no dis to Bob Jordan though.
Don't tell Bob He's really hard to edit.
He's really hard to edit it.
God bless him.
We love him, but Bob Jordan, he's great.
He's great.
But he's yeah, Bob, yeah.
Oh, clay is a fucking mechanism.
Yeah.
He's so crystal clear in his thinking.
So okay.
Well
I'm excited to see.
I think this is going to accelerate for all of us very quickly for a lot of opportunities
because.
you know it's like that light bulb moment and no one's gone to flip the light on and once
that light comes on no one else can hide you can't hide even from a little bit of light in
the in the darkness and that's where naturally these flexible duct has been in the dark
for a while and this is going to be a way to to
That was great.
I wish we were recording right now.
We are.
Can I use that?
Ultimately.
yeah.
Yeah.
It's that's that's good.
Well, the biggest, the biggest things that we have with Superstratum Labs and is it's what
I try to get customers.
Yeah.
The, the homeless is a toxic environment.
They know they're sick.
We got to fix that.
But I really want those customers to
first clean their HVAC systems before they do the rest of the house because if you spend
that money and do all that and then don't change the other, I don't know what, I know
there's same toxins are in there and then you just release them back out into a clean
environment.
It makes no sense.
And so that's why it's so important.
Needs.
when Jeff Jones asked me to write the standards for Microbi Warrior, we came into this
very room right here to write.
I mean, we came in here for two months, eight hours a day straight and came down to brass,
you know, let's figure this out.
We decided that it had to be done first in the process of of restoration project.
We tried to see, well, how will it work if we do it midway or at the end?
And it just didn't line up.
First and then seal it off is the way to go.
Yeah.
Or with your coding, John.
With your coding, I think you could even not seal it and it's fine, right?
Well, yeah, mean, the coating is going to ensure you um even if contaminants get down
there or anything, they're not going to grow on that surface, you know, after that.
through and that's the biggest key, you know.
Ever ever since we've implemented this the superstratum products into our mold
decontamination processes, which we have done a ton of.
Okay.
I've been to Hawaii five times in the last year to do mold, three times to redo mold of
HVAC that was done improperly.
Ever since we've implemented the superstratum products, we have not failed a test.
Yeah.
Beautiful.
Love it.
and I don't know, this is one thing, because this is going to be out there, we talked
about in there, you said disinfected.
You got to be very careful around my product.
And you probably noticed me backtrack on that.
Yes, Artemis can talk about being a disinfectant or that, but they can't talk about being
a cleaner.
Yeah.
know.
EPA regulations, I know, yeah.
call it an oxidizer or what, John?
yes, that's exactly what it's an oxidizer.
You actually, a decontaminant, you know, getting rid of the contaminant, removing.
And so, yes, it's an organic oxidizer to reduce those chemical structures down to where
just, you know, they are not harmful anymore as a toxin, where it can pass the brain
barrier to our DNA that causes those sicknesses.
That's what these chemistries, the HOCl as well as our chlorine dioxide,
we didn't really talk about, know, but those do that.
And then the protectant is a protectant that keeps mold from ever growing on the surface
of that coating.
And since David's equipment ideally sprays all the way through very evenly, now that whole
core or rigid vent is covered with this protectant so that when that if a mold, which mold
is going to get back into the house and pass through the system when they land on that
surface,
with all the other debris of dust and dirt, it will not grow on that surface, even if
condensation somehow gets in there.
Even at the first parts of returns, because you typically only have, if a proper duct is
done right, you only have condensation in the first five feet of a return, because then
the dehumidification happens through the duct.
And then when the pressure comes back, the cold air starts to come back out into the room,
you only have an option
Opportunity to create condensation in that first five to eight feet Otherwise, but we all
know when the flexible doesn't get some unconditioned, know, it could happen in the middle
But that's ideally but by having the protected in all those areas that when that sport
when the Systems off and the spore kind of flies in there and lands It's not going to grow
on those surfaces and that's what everybody wants especially in like I always use this
analogy because everybody can relate when we were in
college now different to my college.
What do we all do is guys we would turn the AC all the way down in our room and open up
the window to yell at the girls outside, but we would grow mold all around the HVAC vents
and all around our window seats.
And I tell every parent to use my products in those two places when they go into their new
dorms and they won't and the parents want they will not have mold problems because about
three months in those kids that are a students all of sudden don't know how
study in their own room and that's why they go to the library and they go to the different
places because it's impossible with all those that molds already started forming they
don't think of it oh molds growing up there nobody thinks that but that is the reasons why
they can't study in their rooms
Military bases is another one that has a big mold issue.
huge.
I've seen p I've seen pictures, it's just awful.
They deserve better.
and you know there's a lot of reasons that because most of the housing was done before air
condition was developed.
So we retrofitted and put like a lean tube on side of these homes and think they were yeah
and just made a toxic environment out of them to the soldiers and the families of our
soldiers and just literally make a second.
No one knows.
We've I've been a basis and try to show them how to do that, but.
It's hard to get them to listen.
I do like the fact that the Change the Area Foundation has got some now amendments in
place and different states are now reacting and that they can get this done right.
I would love them to be using the endurance coating because once they clean it up and they
put that on there, they don't have to worry about it anymore.
That becomes the simplicity of the endurance coating.
When you do the air sorry, just one more question.
Like when you use the sana jet, is it a two time pass through?
It's first uh the disinfectant and then and then the coating.
Uh-huh.
Uh we we insert the hose as far as it'll go.
uh and once again, if there is ducting beyond as far as that that uh ball goes, the hole
on the end will blast it several feet forward.
we actually have video of that on YouTube where you can see where you've we've taken clear
ducting and and you can see just how far it goes.
It's pretty phenomenal.
as far as it'll go, then depress the lever and retract.
My question is this is it two different so do you have to do the first time for the
decontaminant and then the second time for the coating?
Is that what happens?
Yeah.
I assume, David, the first time you do with the building cleaner and the oxidizer and then
you reinsert and put the endurance coating to protect it in and bring it back out.
Is that correct?
That's what we've been doing.
We've been doing the you call it the building building cleaner.
Uh we apply it as an oxidizer, of course.
Uh in this particular case of HVAC.
We apply that, then we allow both dwell time and dry time, and then we apply the the the
coating.
Yeah.
That's great.
Well, thank you guys.
Appreciate it.
Thank you, John.
Yeah, a lot of a lot of content here.
A lot of content to work with.
So Yeah.
All right, Jens.
excited.
Totally excited.
This will fall perfect for us, David, when we go to the show.
You need to send me a bill for my half of that.
What for the fall?
for when are you out there, John?
Are you out at at the experience in the fall?
we're gonna share a booth there.
Well, I'm gonna help him in this.
And then we'll just be able to market our products through him.
That's great.
That's terrific.
And he and I are gonna we're gonna both present together at a one of those at a
presentation.
So yeah.
And both of us are so short winded, I don't know if we can fill the forty five minutes,
you know.
You'll find a way.
You'll find some way.
Your introductions alone will go forty five minutes.
Yeah.
All right, guys.
All right, thanks guys so much.
Nice to meet you, John.
All right, bye, bye guys.
Okay, I need to uh